<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id: tvpvrd.1.xml 257 2010-11-05 22:38:11Z johan162 $ -->
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>
<article
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0">
    <title>tvpowerd</title>
    <refentry
        xml:id="tvpowerd">
        <info>
            <author>
                <personname>
                    <firstname>Johan</firstname>
                    <surname>Persson</surname>
                </personname>
                <email>johan162@gmail.com</email>
                <contrib>Main author and maintainer</contrib>
            </author>
        </info>
        <refmeta>
            <refentrytitle>tvpowerd</refentrytitle>
            <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
            <refmiscinfo
                class="version">@VERSION@</refmiscinfo>
            <refmiscinfo
                class="source">http://sourceforge.net/projects/tvpvrd/</refmiscinfo>
            <refmiscinfo
                class="manual">http://sourceforge.net/projects/tvpvrd/docs/</refmiscinfo>
        </refmeta>
        <refnamediv>
            <refname>tvpowerd</refname>
            <refpurpose>Companion power management daemon for tvpvrd</refpurpose>
        </refnamediv>
        <refsynopsisdiv
            xml:id="tvpowerd.synopsis">
            <title>Synopsis</title>
            <cmdsynopsis>
                <command>tvpowerd</command>
                <arg
                    choice="opt">options...</arg>
            </cmdsynopsis>
        </refsynopsisdiv>
        <refsect1
            xml:id="tvpowerd.description">
            <title>Description</title>
            <para><citerefentry>
                    <refentrytitle>tvpowerd</refentrytitle>
                    <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
                </citerefentry> is a companion daemon that is meant to be used in conjunction with
                the <citerefentry>
                    <refentrytitle>tvpvrd</refentrytitle>
                    <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
                </citerefentry> TV-recording daemon, However, it is vital and <emphasis
                    role="italic">absolutely necessary</emphasis> that this daemon is run on a
                completely different physical server. The reason is that this daemon monitors the
                server doing the TV-recording and turns the power to the recording server on and off
                according to the recording schedule. This will allow the tv-recording server to act
                as a faithful imitation of a real VCR (or Digital PVR). This is good solution if you
                normally have one server that is constantly running (such as you mail- or file
                server) where this daemon can run (it takes virtually no extra CPU and a very small
                memory footprint). The media server doing the recording is often located somewhere
                else , perhaps in the TV-room, and it is desirable to both have it quiet when it is
                not recording as well as saving on the planets energy.</para>
            <para>In order for this to work there are a few, but vital, pre-conditions that must be
                fulfilled.</para>
            <para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Both server must have network connections and have <citerefentry>
                                <refentrytitle>ssh</refentrytitle>
                                <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
                            </citerefentry> installed (this is true for basically all Linux
                            distributions)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The server running the recording daemon must allow the server running
                            the power daemon to login via SSH certificate without password. This is
                            easy done by copying the power servers public SSH key into the file
                            "authorized_keys" on the TV-recording server. This is described in
                            details further down.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The server running the TV recording must support Wake-On-Lan, i.e. it
                            must be possible to turn the power on by sending a special data package
                            to the network card. Virtually all network cards support Wake-On-Lan as
                            well as most motherboards and BIOS. However, it is usually necessary to
                            enable this feature in BIOS (it is often called something similar to
                            "Wake-Up-On-PCI event". </para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </para>
            <para>The rest of the man page will go through the detailed step in setting this
                up.</para>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1
            xml:id="tvpowerd.options">
            <title>Arguments</title>
            <para>The following arguments are supported</para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>-d</option>, <option>--daemon</option>
                            [<emphasis>y</emphasis>|<emphasis>n</emphasis>]</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Determine whether the server should be disconnected from the
                            controlling terminal (a.k.a. running as a daemon). If the server is run
                            as a daemon the logfile cannot be '<emphasis>stdout</emphasis>'. This
                            command line option will override the '<emphasis>daemon</emphasis>'
                            setting in the ini-file. The default setting is to run as a
                            daemon.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>-h</option>, <option>--help</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Print a short help and exit.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>-i</option>, <option>--inifile</option>
                        <filename>filename</filename></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Use the specified file as configuration file. This will override the
                            location specified at compile time. The default location is
                                '<filename>/etc/tvpvrd/tvpvrd.conf</filename>'</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>-l</option>, <option>--logfile</option>
                        <filename>filename</filename></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Define what logfile to use. Two special names can be used
                                <filename>stdout</filename> which will cause the log to be written
                            to the <emphasis>stdout</emphasis> and <filename>syslog</filename> which
                            will cause the logs to be written using the default system log. This
                            command line option will override the '<emphasis>logfile</emphasis>'
                            setting in the ini-file. The default location is
                                '<filename>/tmp/tvpvrd.log</filename>'</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>-V</option>, <option>--verbose</option>
                            [<emphasis>0</emphasis>|<emphasis>1</emphasis>|<emphasis>2</emphasis>|<emphasis>3</emphasis>]</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Log verbosity level. 0 will only log error messages, 1 will log error
                            and info messages, 2 will log errors, info and additional notices
                            finally 3 will also log high volume debug messages.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>-v</option>, <option>--version</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Print program version information and exit.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <para>The default arguments corresponds to starting the server with</para>
            <para>
                <programlisting>tvpvrd -d y -i /etc/tvpowerd/tvpowerd.conf -V 1 -l /tmp/tvpowerd.log</programlisting>
            </para>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
            <title>Starting and stopping the power daemon</title>
            <para>While strictly speaking not necessary the server should normally be started by the
                root user. As soon as the server doesn't need root privileges it will switch to run
                as the user specified in the ini-file, by default this is the user
                    <emphasis>tvpowerd</emphasis>. This user should for security reasons not be the
                'root' user. This user should be a system user without login shell. Such a user can
                normally be created by running the command '<emphasis>useradd</emphasis>'. (If the
                server is installed via the RPM package this user will be automatically
                created)</para>            
                <screen>$> useradd -r tvpowerd</screen>            
            <para>To start the server as root the simplest way is to just call</para>
                <screen>$root> tvpowerd</screen>            
            <para>In order to stop the server and allow it to do a clean shutdown the
                    <code>SIGHUP</code> (or <code>SIGSTOP</code>) signal should be sent to the
                process running the server (assuming tvpvrd has been started as a daemon). The
                distribution includes two support scripts to help with this. </para>
            <para>The first script will be automatically installed in
                    "<filename>/etc/init.d/tvpvrd</filename>" and follows the normal guidelines for
                a "<filename>init.d</filename>" service start/stopping script according to LSB
                (Linux Standard Base). Using this script to start the server the command</para>
                <screen>/etc/init.d/tvpowerd start</screen>            
            <para>is given and to stop the server the command</para>
                <screen>/etc/init.d/tvpowerd stop</screen>           
            <para>should be given. The startup script also supports the "restart" and "status"
                options. </para>            
            <para>Finally if for some reason you don't want to use any of these scripts it is
                possible to manually kill the daemon process by sending the SIGHUP signal via the
                    '<emphasis>kill</emphasis>'command as</para>            
                <screen>$> kill -SIGHUP &lt;pid></screen>            
            <para>where &lt;pid> is the process id of the <emphasis>tvpowerd</emphasis> daemon. Use
                'ps xa' to find the pid or if the server was started as root look in the file
                    '<filename>/var/run/tvpowerd.pid</filename>' </para>
            <para>If the server gives the error message : "<emphasis>Server can not be started. See
                    system log</emphasis>" then more information about the details of the problem
                can be found in the system log, normally <filename>/var/log/messages</filename>. One
                common issue might be a stale lock file (in
                    <filename>/var/run/tvpowerd.pid</filename>) in case the server is not started
                from the root user. The reason is that in order to write these lock files the server
                must run as a root. Since normally the server only runs as a root at the startup
                phase (and then switches over to the selected user) the lock/pid file cannot be
                removed. This is not a problem if the server is again started as root but if the
                server is started from the command line as a non-root user it will complain that the
                lock file already exists. The solution in this case is to manually remove the
                lockfile (as root).</para>
        </refsect1>
        
        <refsect1>
            <title>Configuring ssh</title>
            <para>In order for the daemon to be able to turn the power off on the remote machine it
                must be given root permission. Since we want to avoid to store plain passwords
                (especially the root password) in configuration file the best way to solve this is
                to allow the managing server (the one running the daemon) to log into the recording
                server via ssh certificates.</para>
            <para>This is done by adding the public ssh certificate from the user running the
                tvpowerd to the list of authorized users that can log into the root account on the
                recording daemon.</para>
            <para>Assuming the power daemon is running as user '<code>tvpower</code>' (we assume
                that the user exists and has been created). The following steps will create and
                install the public key on the recording server.</para>
            <para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>On the managing server. Switch to the 'tvpower' user and give the
                            following command</para>
                        <para>
                            <screen>$tvpower>ssh-keygen</screen>
                        </para>
                        <para>When asked for a password just type return (twice) to create a
                            certificate without password. The public certificate will be stored in
                            the file '<filename>~tvpower/.ssh/id_rsa.pub</filename>' </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The next step is to add the content of the
                                '<filename>~tvpower/.ssh/id_rsa.pub</filename>' file to the end of
                            the root users '<filename>.ssh/authorized_keys</filename>' file on the
                            recording server. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>After this is done it should be possible for the <code>tvpower</code>
                            user to login to the recording server as root without giving a password
                            using <command>ssh</command>.  Make sure that it is possible to execute
                            a remote command on the recording server as root user without giving a
                            password. For example the following command (replace the "fake" IP <emphasis
                                role="bold">192.168.0.100</emphasis> with the IP address of your
                            recording server).</para>
                        <para>
                            <screen>$tvpower>ssh root@<emphasis role="bold">192.168.0.100</emphasis> uptime
 14:22pm  up   1:13,  2 users,  load average: 0.00, 0.00, 0.00
$tvpower> _</screen>
                        </para>
                        <para>If this does not work go back and check that no extra blanks or line
                            breaks where inserted by mistake when the public key was copied. Also
                            check that it was really  the public key from the <code>tvpower</code>
                            user on the managing server that was added to the <code>root</code> user
                            on the recording server.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </para>
            <para>It is absolutely critical that the ssh login works before moving on. Without this
                functionality the daemon will no be able to function as intended.</para>
        </refsect1>
        
        <refsect1
            xml:id="tvpowerd.files">
            <title>Files</title>
            <para>Note: The system configuration directory to be used is a compile time settings and
                specified with the '<emphasis>configuration</emphasis>' argument '--sysconfdir'. </para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>&lt;log-directory>/tvpowerd.log</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The logfile. The log-directory is specified in the ini-file. It can
                            also be specified as a command line argument (<option>-l,
                                --logfile</option>) which will then override the ini-file setting.
                            By default the log file will be stored under
                                <filename>/tmp/tvpvrd.log</filename> .(The reason not to use
                                <filename>/var/log/tvpowerd.log</filename> is the fact that the
                            server will not normally run as root and hence will not have write
                            access to this directory.)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>/var/run/tvpowerd.pid</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The pid of the started 'tvpvrd' server. This is used to easily find
                            the pid in order to shutdown the server. This is used by the
                                <emphasis>stop-tvpvrd</emphasis> script. Note that in order to use
                            this directory the daemon has to be started by the root user. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>/etc/tvpowerd/tvpowerd.conf</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Default configuration file</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
            <title>Limitations</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The <filename>/var/run/tvpowerd.pid</filename> file is not removed
                            after the program has shut down if the effective user is any other than
                            'root', (by default the server will switch to the 'tvpvrd' user) since
                            only root has access to <filename>/var/run</filename></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>All information and error messages are hard coded in English and
                            cannot be easily localized.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
            <title>Notes</title>
            <para>Any errors that are discovered in the startup phase before a logfile has been
                established will be written to the default system log (normally
                    <filename>/var/log/messages</filename>) </para>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
            <title>Resources</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>SourceForge: &lt;http://sourceforge.net/projects/tvpvrd/></para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
            <title>Author</title>
            <para>Written and maintained by Johan Persson &lt;johan162@gmail.com></para>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
            <title>Copyright</title>
            <para>Free use of this software is granted under the terms of the GNU General Public
                License (GPL v3)., see the file COPYING included in the distribution archive for
                details.</para>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1
            xml:id="tvpowerd.seealso">
            <title>See also</title>
            <para><citerefentry>
                    <refentrytitle>tvpvrd</refentrytitle>
                    <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
                </citerefentry></para>
        </refsect1>
    </refentry>
</article>
