<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>
<article
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0">
    <title>tvpvrd</title>
    <refentry
        xml:id="tvpvrd">
        <info>
            <author>
                <personname>
                    <firstname>Johan</firstname>
                    <surname>Persson</surname>
                </personname>
                <email>johan162@gmail.com</email>
                <contrib>Main author and maintainer</contrib>
            </author>
        </info>
        <refmeta>
            <refentrytitle>tvpvrd</refentrytitle>
            <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
            <refmiscinfo
                class="version">@VERSION@</refmiscinfo>
            <refmiscinfo
                class="source">http://sourceforge.net/projects/tvpvrd/</refmiscinfo>
            <refmiscinfo
                class="manual">http://sourceforge.net/projects/tvpvrd/docs/</refmiscinfo>
        </refmeta>
        <refnamediv>
            <refname>tvpvrd</refname>
            <refpurpose>TV Personal Video Recorder Server/Daemon</refpurpose>
        </refnamediv>
        <refsynopsisdiv
            xml:id="tvpvrd.synopsis">
            <title>Synopsis</title>
            <cmdsynopsis>
                <command>tvpvrd</command>
                <arg
                    choice="opt">options...</arg>
            </cmdsynopsis>
        </refsynopsisdiv>
        <refsect1
            xml:id="tvpvrd.description">
            <title>Description</title>
            <para>The <citerefentry>
                    <refentrytitle>tvpvrd</refentrytitle>
                    <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
                </citerefentry> command starts a video recording server that will make use of one or
                more installed TV-Capture cards and, following a specified schedule, will record
                broadcasted and encoded streams from the capture card to disk. In effect a digital
                version of a programmable VHS. In a similar way as a VCR the daemon also have the
                capability to shutdown and power on the server in time for recordings (see the
                auto-shutdown section below). In the same way as the old-fashioned VHS it has the
                capability to turn off the power of the server and wake it up in time for a
                recording in a fully automated way (by using the BIOS wakeup alarm).</para>
            <para>The original HW MPEG2 encoded videofile (from the capture card) can then be
                optionally transcoded (using <citerefentry>
                    <refentrytitle>ffmpeg</refentrytitle>
                    <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
                </citerefentry> ) to a more efficient format by the daemon. The specific details on
                both the initial HW encoder settings as well as the transcoding options are bundled
                in a user configurable 'profile'. The daemon supports the usage of  multiple
                profiles. </para>
            <para>Each recording is done using one (or multiple) profiles. Each recording will
                always have at least one profile, the primary profile. In this way it is possible to
                create multiple transcoded versions of one recording, for example one high quality
                version for viewing on a computer and one low quality versions for viewing on a
                mobile device. By default the distribution includes six profiles 'high', 'normal',
                'low' without transcoding and 'thigh', 'tnormal', 'tlow' with transcoding enabled.
                Additional profiles can easily be added by the user. A profile is specified in the
                traditional ini-file text file format and is stored under the 'profiles' directory
                which is a subdirectory to the settings directory (normally
                    <filename>/etc/tvpvrd</filename>). Each setting in the profile is well
                documented in the profiles. </para>
            <para>The primary interface to the server is via a TCP/IP connection to the server
                running '<emphasis>tvpvrd</emphasis>' via a dedicated port (by default 9300). The
                server is controlled via a simple (but efficient) command language which allows
                manipulation of future recordings and various other administrative tasks. All
                commands are extensively described in the section 'Command language' below. </para>
            <para>As an optional way there is also a native basic WEB-interface that allows a
                limited number of commands such as basic adding of new recording, deleting existing
                recordings, viewing status, showing upcoming recordings etc. The WEB-interface must
                be enabled in the ini-file since it is by default disabled. The WEB interface is
                accessed on port number (port+1) i.e one more than the port number specified for the
                command interface. This means that by default the WEB-interface is available on port
                9301. The WEB-interface can optionally require a separate login as specified in the
                configuration file. </para>
            <para>To access the WEB interface from a browser simple give the server address and port
                number. For example to access the daemon on the server "<code>localhost</code>" with
                the default port number use URL "<filename>http://localhost:9301</filename>". </para>
            <para>The look and feel of the WEB-interface is entirely controlled by a CSS style sheet
                stored in the configuration directory (usually specified as
                    <filename>/etc</filename>). This is the same place as where the configuration
                file is stored. This means it is straightforward to change the look and feel from
                the default colors and layout.</para>
            <para>The WEB interface will also automatically adapt when it detects that a mobile
                phone browser is trying to access the interface to a format more suitable for the
                smaller screen on mobile phones. By necessity this means that only a subset of the
                full command set is available from the browser on a phone in order to keep the
                interface simple. The detection is based on the header that the browser sends and
                should detect most phones. However, it is possible that some browsers used on mobile
                phone will not be detected as mobile browsers and then the normal WEB interface will
                be used.</para>
            <para>The recordings specified are stored in a database which is a plain text file in
                XML format using UTF-8 character encoding.</para>
            <para>Recorded and transcoded files are stored in a predefined directory structure. The
                base directory for this directory structure is defined in the configuration file,
                see also the section "Directory Structure" below.</para>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1
            xml:id="tvpvrd.options">
            <title>Arguments</title>
            <para>The following command line arguments are supported when starting the daemon</para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>-d</option>, <option>--daemon</option>
                            [<emphasis>y</emphasis>|<emphasis>n</emphasis>]</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Determine whether the server should be disconnected from the
                            controlling terminal (a.k.a. running as a daemon). If the server is run
                            as a daemon the logfile cannot be '<emphasis>stdout</emphasis>'. This
                            command line option will override the '<emphasis>daemon</emphasis>'
                            setting in the ini-file. The default setting is to run as a
                            daemon.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>-f</option>, <option>--xmldbfile</option>
                        <filename>filename</filename></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Use the specified file as the database file where all the specified
                            recordings are stored in XML format. This command line option will
                            override the '<emphasis>xmldbfile</emphasis>' setting in the ini-file.
                            The default location is '&lt;dataroot>/xmldb/tvpvrd_db.xml' </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>-h</option>, <option>--help</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Print a short help and exit.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>-i</option>, <option>--inifile</option>
                        <filename>filename</filename></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Use the specified file as configuration file. This will override the
                            location specified at compile time. The default location is
                                '<filename>/etc/tvpvrd/tvpvrd.conf</filename>'</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>-l</option>, <option>--logfile</option>
                        <filename>filename</filename></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Define the name of the logfile. Two special names can be used,
                                <filename>stdout</filename> which will cause the log to be written
                            to the <emphasis>stdout</emphasis> and <filename>syslog</filename> which
                            will cause the logs to be written using the default system logger. This
                            command line option will override the '<emphasis>logfile</emphasis>'
                            setting in the ini-file. The default location is
                                '<filename>/tmp/tvpvrd.log</filename>'</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>
                        <option>-p</option>, <option>--port</option>
                        <emphasis>nnnn</emphasis>
                    </term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Specify what TCP/IP port number that the server will listening on.
                            This will override the '<emphasis>port</emphasis>' setting in the
                            ini-file. By default this is port 9300. The port number of the
                            WEB-interface will be <emphasis>nnnn</emphasis>+1 so by default the
                            WEB-interface will be available on port 9301.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>-s</option>, <option>--slave</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Run the server in slave configuration. This will allow the server to
                            be running on a machine with no video cards and be restricted to only do
                            video transcodings.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>-V</option>, <option>--verbose</option>
                            [<emphasis>0</emphasis>|<emphasis>1</emphasis>|<emphasis>2</emphasis>|<emphasis>3</emphasis>]</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Log verbosity level. 0 will only log error messages, 1 will log error
                            and info messages, 2 will log errors, info and additional notices
                            finally 3 will also log (possibly) high volume debug messages.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>-v</option>, <option>--version</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Print program version information and exit.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>-x</option>, <option>--xawtvrc</option>
                        <filename>filename</filename></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Use the specified file to read the station names. The station name
                            file maps the standardized frequency channel names to the more commonly
                            used station names. See the section "Stations, channels and frequencies"
                            below for more information. This will override the setting in the
                            ini-file. The default location is
                            '<filename>/etc/X11/xawtvrc</filename>'</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <para>The default arguments corresponds to starting the server with</para>
            <para>
                <programlisting>tvpvrd -d y -f tvpvrd_db.xml -i /etc/tvpvrd/tvpvrd.conf -p 9300 -V 1 -x /etc/X11/xawtvrc</programlisting>
            </para>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
            <title>Starting and stopping the server</title>
            <para>While strictly speaking not necessary the server should normally be started by the
                root user. As soon as the server doesn't need root privileges it will switch to run
                as the user specified in the ini-file, by default this is the user
                    <emphasis>tvpvrd</emphasis>. This user should for security reasons not be the
                'root' user. This user should be a system user without login shell. Such a user can
                normally be created by running the command '<emphasis>useradd</emphasis>'. (If the
                server is installed via the RPM package this user will be automatically
                created).</para>
            <para>Note: If you want to use the automatic shutdown/wakeup functionality the daemon
                must be run as root (since only root has privileges to access the BIOS wakeup
                functionality)</para>            
                <screen>$> useradd -r tvpvrd</screen>            
            <para>To start the server as root the simplest way is to just call</para>
                <screen>$root> tvpvrd</screen>            
            <para>In order to stop the server and allow it to do a clean shutdown the SIGHUP (or
                SIGSTOP) signal should be sent to the process running the server (assuming tvpvrd
                has been started as a daemon). The distribution includes two support scripts to help
                with this. </para>
            <para>The first script will be automatically installed in
                    "<filename>/etc/init.d/tvpvrd</filename>" and follows the normal guidelines for
                a "<filename>init.d</filename>" service start/stopping script according to LSB
                (Linux Standard Base). Using this script to start the server the command</para>
                <screen>/etc/init.d/tvpvrd start</screen>            
            <para>is given and to stop the server the command</para>
                <screen>/etc/init.d/tvpvrd stop</screen>           
            <para>should be given. The startup script also supports the "restart" and "status"
                options.</para>
            <para>The second script is '<filename>stop-tvpvrd</filename>' which will read the server
                process pid from '<filename>/var/run/tvpvrd.pid</filename>' and send the SIGHUP
                signal.</para>
            <para>In order to stop the server first switch to root user and then use the
                command</para>            
                <screen>$root> stop-tvpvrd</screen>            
            <para>Finally if for some reason you don't want to use any of these scripts it is
                possible to manually kill the daemon process by sending the SIGHUP signal via the
                    '<emphasis>kill</emphasis>'command as</para>            
                <screen>$> kill -SIGHUP &lt;pid></screen>            
            <para>where &lt;pid> is the process id of the <emphasis>tvpvrd</emphasis> daemon. Use
                'ps xa' to find the pid or if the server was started as root look in the file
                    '<filename>/var/run/tvpvrd.pid</filename>' </para>
            <para>When the server is shutdown, depending on the "Kill transcoding flag" (see the
                    <option>-ktf</option> command), any on-going transcodings will be shutdown. Any
                potential ongoing recordings will be aborted and the recordings up to the time the
                recording is shutdown will be left in the '<filename>&lt;data-dir>/vtmp</filename>'
                directory and must be removed manually.</para>
            <para>If the server gives the error message : "<emphasis>Server can not be started. See
                    system log</emphasis>" then more information about the details of the problem
                can be found in the system log, normally <filename>/var/log/messages</filename>. One
                common issue might be a stale lock file (in
                <filename>/var/run/tvpvrd.pid</filename>) in case the server is not started from the
                root user. The reason is that in order to write these lock files the server must run
                as a root. Since normally the server only runs as a root at the startup phase (and
                then switches over to the selected user) the lock/pid file cannot be removed. This
                is not a problem if the server is again started as root but if the server is started
                from the command line as a non-root user it will complain that the lock file already
                exists. The solution in this case is to manually remove the lockfile (as
                root).</para>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
            <title>Automatic shutdown and startup of the server</title>
            <para>In the same way as a VCR (or a modern HD recorder) has the capability to shut down
                and power on in time for recording the tvpvrd can do this with the server it is
                running on. The daemon package has two radically different way to do this and
                depending on your preference (and/or HW) either way can be chosen. The server
                supports either the usage of the internal BIOS real time clock using a wakeup alarm
                or running a power management daemon (<command>tvpowerd</command>) on a separate
                server. If you have a reasonable modern server (say 2005 or newer) it will most
                likely support BIOS wakeup alarm and since that is the easiest method we strongly
                recommend you use that method.</para>
            <refsect2>
                <title>Method 1: Using the BIOS wakeup alarm on the server running the tvpvrd
                    daemon</title>
                <para>To use this method it is first important to recognize that the daemon must be
                    running as user '<code>root</code>' in order to have the privilege to shut down
                    the server.</para>
                <para>To enable this feature it must first be enabled in the configuration file
                    under the section <code>[shutdown]</code> . By default this feature is disabled.
                    There are then some basic parameters that should be checked according to
                    preference. For example the parameter <code>ignore_users</code> will determine
                    if the shutdown should still happen if there are user logged in to the server or
                    not. All the available parameters are fully specified and documented in the
                    default configuration file.</para>
                <para>To make this work the daemon assumes that the RTC (BIOS Real Time Clock)
                    presents an interface on the
                    "<filename>/sys/class/rtc/rtc0/wakealarm</filename>" that can be used to set the
                    time in seconds since Epoc when the server should wake up if it is powered off.
                    In some BIOS it is also necessary to first enable the wakeup alarm by changing
                    some default setting (check your BIOS documentation).</para>
                <para>In order not to miss the recording the server is woken up a little bit before
                    the actual recording time. By default this is 180 sec which should be enough
                    time for even old servers to fully wake up. This pre-wakeup time is configurable
                    in the configuration file. </para>
                <para>The actual shutdown of the server is done by the
                        "<filename>shutdown.sh</filename>" script stored in the configuration
                    directory. In the distribution this is included as a template
                        "<filename>shutdown.sh.template</filename>" which can then be augmented. By
                    default the script initiates a complete server shutdown and if that is enough
                    the template can just be copied and renamed. </para>
                <para>If the server is reasonable new it might be possible to do a sleep (or
                    hibernate) instead but in that case we would recommend using the second method
                    of auto-shutdown using the separate "<command>tvpowerd</command>" as described
                    below. Please note that there are some special precautions that must be taken to
                    use sleep or hibernation mode since the ivtv-driver is not power management
                    aware. So unless absolutely necessary please use the safe and always working
                    method of just doing a complete shutdown. See <citerefentry>
                        <refentrytitle>tvpowerd</refentrytitle>
                        <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
                    </citerefentry>  for more details.</para>                
            </refsect2>
            <refsect2>
                <title>Method 2: Using the tvpowerd-daemon on a separate server</title>
                <para>Since some older motherboards does not have a working BIOS wakeup clock and
                    for the case where you rather sleep (or hibernate) the server instead of
                    shutting it down the package gives an alternative auto-shutdown method using the
                        "<command>tvpowerd</command>" daemon. This is a separate daemon that must be
                    run on a separate server. This daemon will then communicate with the server
                    running the recording daemon and shut the server down and power it on according
                    to the recording schedule. The power on will be done using Wakeup-On-LAN so this
                    must be enabled in the BIOS on the recording server. There is a complete
                    separate manual page describing all the details on how to use this daemon in <citerefentry>
                        <refentrytitle>tvpowerd</refentrytitle>
                        <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
                    </citerefentry>
                </para>
            </refsect2>
            <refsect2>
                <title>When shall I use Method 1 and when shall I use Method 2 ?</title>
                <para>If only one server is available and the motherboard supports the RTC wakeup
                    alarm then method 1 is the preferred way. Even if you have multiple servers
                    available it is still easier to use method 1.  However there is one circumstance
                    where it might be more practically to use the <command>tvpowerd</command>
                    standalone daemon. For the common case where you have a NFS or SMB file share
                    exposed from the recording server, for example to be able to view the videos on
                    another computer, there are all kinds off issues if the SMB or NFS server is
                    just shut down without the share unmounted. Especially the NFS protocol is
                    notoriously bad in handling a disconnected server without a proper unmount.
                    Running the separate <command>tvpowerd</command> daemon on the client will allow
                    you to put in the necessary unmount commands in the shutdown script (assuming
                    the tvpowerd is running on the server mounting shares). </para>
                <para>In future releases of <command>tvpvrd</command> it will be possible to run
                    user selectable scripts on clients to the recording server at the shutdown time.
                    This can then be used to, for example, give the client notification that the
                    recording server is shutting down and then be able to do any necessary unmounts
                    or other cleanup activities.</para>
                <para>In the case where you rather want to suspend to RAM/DISK then it is also
                    necessary to run the separate <command>tvpowerd</command> daemon. The main
                    reason here is that since the ivtv-drivers that resides in the kernel is not
                    power management aware they must therefore be unloaded before the server is put
                    into hibernation and then reloaded when the server is woken up. This can be (and
                    is) all taken care of in the shutdown scripts for the tvpowerd daemon. However,
                    there is really no practical reason to put the recording server in
                    sleep/hibernation state compare with a full shutdown. The only thing gained is
                    faster startup time which for these use-cases are not really interesting (nor
                    necessary).</para>
            </refsect2>            
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
            <title>Running as master or slave</title>
            <para>Normally the daemon will do necessary checks to verify that one or several video
                cards are present in order to startup. If no video cards are found the server will
                print an error message and terminate. However it is still possible to run the daemon
                on a server with no video cards by running the server in <emphasis
                    role="italic">slave</emphasis> mode. This will restrict the functionality of the
                server to only transcoding and status information commands.</para>
            <para>The primary purpose of running the server in slave configuration is to make it
                possible to use several servers to transcode video files. There are three commands "<emphasis
                    role="bold">tf</emphasis>" (<emphasis
                    role="italic">transcode file</emphasis>), "<emphasis
                    role="bold">tl</emphasis>" (<emphasis
                    role="italic">transcode list</emphasis>) and "<emphasis
                    role="bold">td</emphasis>" (<emphasis
                    role="italic">transcode directory</emphasis>) that can be used to transcode one
                or more files in slave mode (see the command section below for details).</para>
            <para>In future version of the server there will be possibility to configure a load
                balancing setup among several servers for the transcoding but as of version 1.x this
                has to be done manually.</para>
            <para>The server can be run in slave mode by either giving the "<option>-s</option>"
                option when starting the server or by setting the configuration alternative
                    "<option>master=no</option>" in the configuration file.</para>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
            <title>Connecting to the server</title>
            <para>Once the server is running the easiest way to connect to the server is by using
                the '<emphasis>telnet</emphasis>' program. Assuming that the
                    <emphasis>tvpvrd</emphasis> server is running on the localhost the following
                command will connect to the server (assuming the default port 9300 has not been
                changed in the ini-file (e.g. <filename>/etc/tvpvrd.conf</filename>) or by a command
                line argument).</para>            
                <screen>$> telnet localhost 9300</screen>            
            <para>After a successful connection the server will reply with a short information
                message. The full returned information message at the connection time should look
                something similar to the following (your version and build might be
                different):</para>
            <screen>Welcome to tvpvrd-2.3.0  [Server] (build:20101225.191)
You are user number 1 out of 4 allowed.
Type 'exit' to disconnect.
Type 'h' to list available commands.
Connection will be closed after 30 min of inactivity.
</screen>
            <para>If password protection (see section "Security" below) the welcome message is not
                be shown until the correct password has been specified. Instead when password
                protection is enabled the connection sequence looks like this</para>
            
                <screen>$> telnet localhost 9300
Password:<emphasis role="bold">xxxxxxx</emphasis>
Welcome to tvpvrd-2.3.0  [Server] (build:20101225.191)
You are user number 1 out of 4 allowed.
Type 'exit' to disconnect.
Type 'h' to list available commands.
Connection will be closed after 30 min of inactivity.
</screen>
            
            <para>This means that the correct server password has to be given before the welcome
                message is seen. The server is now ready to accept commands on this
                connection.</para>
            <para>To disconnect to the server just type '<command>exit</command>'</para>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
            <title>The recording and transcoding process</title>
            <para>The recording process refers to the process of saving the generated MPRG2 video
                stream from the capture card to a file.</para>
            <para>The transcoding process refers to the re-coding of the original MPEG2 video stream
                to a more efficient format, usually an MPEG4 container using H.264 video codec (the
                default in the distributed profiles). Depending on the quality settings it is common
                to see reduction in original file size with 75%.</para>
            <para>The transcoding process is very CPU-intensive and with the default settings in the
                distribution the normal profile will require anywhere between roughly 1.5 times the
                original recording length to transcode on a pentium dual core to roughly 0.5 times
                the recording length on a newer i3 or i5 Intel CPU. With a high end Intel multi-core
                i7 CPU and some basic setting the transcoding time can be down to ~0.3 times the
                length of the original recording.</para>
            <para>In order not to make the machine totally unresponsive the ini-file specifies a
                maximum load on the server for a transcoding to start in order not to load the
                server with too many parallel transcoding processes. The transcoding process is also
                run with a 'nice' value of 20 to have the transcoding process interfere as little as
                possible with any interactive use on the server. If the load is too high the
                transcoding processes will be put in a queue waiting for the load to become
                acceptable. Note that the serer will not wait forever and if the load has not
                dropped below the threshold for a certain time (as specified by the
                    <code>max_waiting_time_to_transcode</code> setting in the ini-file) the
                transcoding will be cancelled and the original MPEG2 file left alone.</para>
            <para>When a recording is started a temporary directory will be created under
                    '<filename>&lt;data-dir>/vtmp/vid&lt;n>/</filename>' where &lt;n> is the number
                of the video card used. The name of the temporary directory will be the same as the
                base name of the recording. The MPEG2 stream is read from the video card and stored
                in a file in the temporary directory with the same name as the title (converted to
                lower case) with the suffix ".mpg".</para>
            <para>If multiple profiles are specified there exists an ambiguity on what HW MPEG2
                parameters to use in case they are different among the selected profiles. The server
                resolves this by using the HW parameters from the profile with the highest specified
                video bitrate. This is motivated by the fact that using high quality encoder
                settings on a low original bitrate can never give a good result.</para>
            <para>When the recording has stopped the transcoding profile(s) is read and the
                transcoding is started after a check that the server load is not higher than the
                maximum allowed load in order to start a transcoding. If the load is too high the
                transcoding is put in a queue of waiting transcodings that will be started when the
                server load allows the transcoding to start. One transcoding will be made for each
                of the associated profiles of this recording.</para>
            <para>As a special case no transcoding will be made if the '<emphasis>ffmpeg</emphasis>'
                profile bitrate is set to 0 Mbps in the profile. In this case only the original
                MPEG2 video file will be kept.</para>
            <para>Once a transcoding has finished the resulting MP4 file will be moved either to the
                directory '<filename>&lt;data-dir>/mp4/&lt;profile>/</filename>' with the same file
                basename as the title but with the filename suffix ".mp4"  or directly under
                    <filename>'&lt;data-dir>/mp4/'</filename> depending whether or not
                subdirectories should be used for each profile (see setting file).</para>
            <para>When all the transcodings have been done and if the profile defines that the
                original MPEG2 video stream should be kept it is moved to the directory
                    '<filename>&lt;data-dir>/mp2/</filename>'. After that the temporary directory
                (and the original MPEG2 file) is deleted.</para>
            <para>Another possibility is to do the recording first and later decide to transcode one
                or several video files. This is done by giving a separate transcode command to the
                server and specify the full file path to the file to be transcoded. In order to make
                this as convenient as possible there are three variants of this. One variant is to
                transcode one video file, the other is to specify a directory where all the files in
                that directory will be transcoded. The final way is to store a number of video file
                names in a text file and use that text file as an input list of the files to
                transcode. See the command description below for the commands "<option>tf</option>",
                    "<option>td</option>" and "<option>tl</option>".</para>
            <para>Note that it is possible to get notify by mail when a transcoding has finished.
                The email address used is specified in the <filename>ini-file</filename></para>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
            <title>Directory structure</title>
            <para>The root directory for where the video files (recordings) are stored is specified
                in the ini-file (e.g. <filename>/etc/tvpvrd/tvpvrd.conf</filename>). Under this root
                directory the following subdirectories and files are automatically created by the
                server:</para>
            <para>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><filename>&lt;dataroot>/mp2</filename></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>If the profile specifies that the original MP2 files recorded from
                                the capture card should be saved they are stored under this
                                directory.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><filename>&lt;dataroot>/mp4/&lt;profile></filename></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The transcoded original MPEG2 files are by default placed under a
                                subdirectory under MP4 corresponding to the name of the profile used
                                for the transcoding. This can be changed to a flat structure instead
                                which will cause all transcoded files to be placed directly under
                                the <filename>mp4/</filename> ignoring the profile name. This is
                                done by setting the option '<code>use_profile_directories</code>' to
                                false in the ini-file.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><filename>&lt;dataroot>/stats/&lt;profile>.stats</filename></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The statistics recorded while transcoding is stored in a file
                                corresponding to the name of the profile.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><filename>&lt;dataroot>/vtmp</filename></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Temporary video directory used while recording and transcoding is
                                performed. Each capture card used has its own subdirectory named
                                    '<filename>vid</filename>'<emphasis
                                    role="italic">n</emphasis>. Where '<emphasis
                                    role="italic">n</emphasis>' is the number for the video card in
                                that folder.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><filename>&lt;dataroot>/xmldb/tvpvrd_db.xml</filename></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The XML DB file that holds the database for all defined
                                recordings.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </para>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
            <title>Security</title>
            <para>In order to prevent unauthorized access to the server the server have a basic
                password protection. This means that a password can be configured to be used before
                a client can start giving command to the server. This is configured in the ini-file.
                The configuration uses the same password for all clients so the server does not
                support multiple users/multiple password. Since the password is stored in plain text
                format the configuration file should have restricted access. This should not be
                considered strong security but rather a weak "stop-messing-with-my-recordings"
                protection.</para>
            <para>The setting whether password should be used or not and the actual password is
                specified in the ini-file. </para>
            <para>After connecting to the server when the password has been enabled the first string
                sent back from the server will be the single string:</para>
            
                <screen>Password:</screen>
            <para>The rest of the reply is the same as when no password is used.</para>
            <para>For the WEB-interface it is also possible to specify a different user and password
                to allow the usage of the WEB GUI.</para>
            
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
            <title>Stations, channels and frequencies</title>
            <para>All TV stations are broadcasted on a local unique frequency. The frequency
                spectrum is a natural resource that divided in internationally standardized fixed
                width channels. A channel is the same as a specified frequency. The distance between
                each assigned frequency is different depending on both the frequency area and the TV
                standard used. This depends on the fact that different TV standard requires
                different bandwidth. This channel division is also different depending on the
                geographic location. </para>
            <para>It is important to realize that these fixed frequencies are assigned according to
                international standards. In each city (and city area) the broadcasting company is
                then responsible for assigning local stations to appropriate frequency channels.
                This is the difference between station and channel names. The channel names are
                standardized names that have short name with 2 to 5 characters, for example 'SE14'.
                Even though the frequency division is standardized the exact channel names are not
                always given with the assigned names. For example a broadcasting company might claim
                (for example on their home page) that the station 'BBC1' in a certain area can be
                found on channel '14' when they actually should have said that the station can be
                found on channel 'SE14' which is the official name of this channel.</para>
            <para>To further complicate matters different countries uses different standardized
                frequency maps. The program has built in knowledge of the frequency channels
                available in the following geographic areas</para>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>FREQMAP_EUROPEWEST, Western europe</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>FREQMAP_EUROPEEAST, Eastern Europe</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>FREQMAP_FRANCE, France</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>FREQMAP_IRELAND, Ireland</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>FREQMAP_ITALY, Italy</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>FREQMAP_AUSTRALIA, Australia</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>FREQMAP_NEWZEALAND, New Zealand</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>FREQMAP_USBCAST, United States air frequencies</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>FREQMAP_USCABLE, United States cable frequencies</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <para>Since the program has no way to automatically know which map to use this must be
                specified in the application ini-file. This map file lists all the defined
                frequencies and the official name for that country and frequency.</para>
            <para>In order to record a specific station the tuner on the capture card must be tuned
                to the correct frequency channel used by the station we want to record. Since it is
                a lot easier to use the station names, for example "BBC1", than the official name on
                the frequency channel, e.g. SE14, the program uses yet another mapping file so it is
                possible to use station names when recording instead of frequency channels. This is
                the way most people think about "TV-Stations".</para>
            <para>In order for maximum re-use <emphasis>tvpvrd</emphasis> uses the same format of
                the station/channel mapping file as is done in '<emphasis>xawtvrc</emphasis>'. This
                is a plain text file using ini-file format. In the distribution an example file is
                included. Normally your TV provider provides a channel plan for your area.
                Unfortunately, to make things a bit more difficult some broadcasting company is not
                following the international naming convention. </para>
            <para>If you are already viewing TV on your computer chances are very high that you
                already have this 'xawtvrc' ini-file since it is used by many of the available TV
                viewing programs. Common location for this file is either
                    '<filename>/etc/X11/xawtvrc</filename>' or in your home directory
                    '<filename>.xawtvrc</filename>'.</para>
            <para>An example of a station-channel mapping file is shown below (this mapping file
                happens to be the maps for a large Swedish distributor in the Stockholm
                region):</para>
            
                <screen>[Kanal5]
channel = SE11
[Kanal8]
channel = 57
[Kanal9]
channel = S36
[MTV]
channel = SE16
[SVT24]
channel = E10
[SVTB/Kunsk]
channel = SE13
[TV1]
channel = E5
[TV2]
channel = E7
[TV3]
channel = E11
[TV4]
channel = E6
[TV4+]
channel = SE14
[TV6]
channel = E8
</screen>
            <para>The mapping above says that for example the station "Kanal5" can be found on
                frequency channel SE11. This mapping will then make it possible to use the name
                "Kanal5" when specifying recordings which is a lot easier than to remember that this
                station is on channel "SE11".</para>
            
            <para>In some Unix distributions there are automatic frequency scanning helper programs
                (for example <citerefentry>
                    <refentrytitle>scantv</refentrytitle>
                    <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
                </citerefentry>) which will search through a given frequency map and list all
                channels where a broadcasting was find (this is identified as a high enough signal
                strength). For example SuSE distribution have a TV channel scanning setup in the
                yast2 configuration tool. The result of this channel scan is usually stored in a
                file named '<filename>xawtvrc</filename>'. This is usually stored in either
                    '<filename>/etc/X11/xawtvrc</filename>' or in you home directory, usually as
                    '<filename>~/.awtvrc</filename>'. However the actual station names you want to
                use for the channels must of course be manually given. </para>
            <para>The somewhat strange name of the map file comes from an ancient TV viewer program
                under X11 which was/(is) called 'xawtv'. For historic reason this name has
                stayed.</para>
            <para>While it is possible to use either the station name or the channel name in a
                recording there must be a '<filename>xawtvrc</filename>' file in order for the
                server to start properly. If the station file cannot be found an error message will
                be printed and the server will not start.</para>
            <para>The location of this file is normally specified in the ini-file but the location
                can also be overridden with command line argument (<option>-x</option>) when the
                server is started (see Options) which will override the setting in the
                ini-file.</para>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
            <title>Selecting alternative video inputs as source for the encoding</title>
            <para>A video capture card has normally several possible input to the HW MP2 encoder.
                When encoding TV the tuner is usually the selected input. However most cards also
                have one or several external connects that can be used to encode other video
                sources. For example Hauppauge analogue cards have one or more (depending on the
                card) S-Video inputs that could be used as source for the video encoding.</para>
            <para>The first thing to do if one wants to use one of these alternative input sources
                is to determine exactly what input sources the combination of card and low level
                driver supports. This can be done with the help of the command <command>li</command>
                . This will list all the available input sources for the specified video card. For
                example if your server have a Hauppauge 350 installed as the first card giving the
                command</para>
            <para><command>li 0</command></para>
            <para>would generate output similar to</para>
            
                <screen>Hauppauge WinTV PVR-350
00 :*(tuner) Tuner 1
01 : (camera) S-Video 1
02 : (camera) Composite 1
03 : (camera) S-Video 2
04 : (camera) Composite 2
05 : (camera) Composite 3</screen>
            
            <para>This is a list of  all possible video sources supported by the card. The current
                selected source is shown with an asterix just to the left of the type of
                input.</para>
            <para>In order to use one of these inputs as the source for the recoding instead of the
                standard tuner a special station name is used "<emphasis
                    role="italic">_inpXY</emphasis>". The 'X' should be replaced by the video card
                to be used (starting at 0) and the 'Y' should be replaced by the index for the
                wanted input source. So for example going back to the previous Hauppauge 350 above a
                meta station name of "<code>_inp04</code>" would use the composite 2 input source
                (assuming the card is the first card, i.e. 0).</para>
            <para>In order for the server to know which input belongs to the tuner this is specified
                in the config file with the setting <emphasis
                    role="italic">tuner_input_index</emphasis>, by default this is 0. Since there is
                only one setting this implies that all cards use the same index for the tuner. This
                is a limitation of the current implementation. If you have several cards where the
                tuner is located at different input indexes then the server can only work correctly
                on one card. This is a very minor limitation since the number of users with multiple
                cards with tuners on other indexes than 0 can be assumed to be very small.</para>
            <para>A final example will make this crystal clear. Assume we want to record a CCTV
                camer that is connected to composite input 1 on our Hauppauge 350 card. To
                immediately start recording for 30 min using the default profile we could give the
                command</para>
            
                <screen>q _inp02 00:30 cctv_camera_one</screen>
            
            <para>the command above would immediately start a recording using card 0 and input with
                index 2, i.e.. the "<code>Composite 1</code>" input. The recording will be stored
                with the name "<code>cctv_camera_one.mp4</code>" (assuming the default profile is
                setup to do transcoding to MP4 format).</para>
            <para>There is also an option to handle channel switching on a cable box. This is
                described in the "Adding user "hooks" for special processing" section below.</para>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
            <title>Managing notifications mails</title>
            <para>When configuring the daemon it is possible to set options that will send
                notification mails on important events in the daemon. This could be notifications on
                errors that occurred but also notifications on that a transcoding was finished or
                that the server was shutdown automatically while waiting for the next
                recording.</para>
            <para>All mail settings are specified in the "<code>[mail]</code>" section of the
                configuration file.</para>
            <para>Sending mails can be done by either using a specified SMTP server (in the
                configuration file) or by using the systems own "<command>mail</command>" command.
                However, if you chose the latter you cannot ask the server to send HTML formatted
                mails (by setting the configuration "<code>use_html=yes</code>"), only plain text
                mail with the systems built in "<command>mail</command>" command. </para>
            <para>The actual text (and formatting in case of HTML mails) are controlled by templates
                that are stored in the general configuration directory. All templates are prefixed
                by "<code>mail_*</code>". The templates exists in both a "<code>*.txt</code>" and a
                    "<code>*.html</code>" version. The text version is used when sending plain text
                messages and the HTML version when sending HTML formatted mails. In complying with
                internet mail standards the plain version is also included in the mail even when
                sending HTML formatted mails so that mail clients that are unable to display HTML
                format will use the plain text version instead. (HTML mails are formatted according
                to internet standard MIME attachment rules.)</para>
            <para>At the time of this writing the following templates are used by the daemon</para>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><code>mail_shutdown.*</code> Used when sending notifications on
                            automatic server shutdown</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><code>mail_transcend.*</code> Used when sending notifications when
                            transcoding has finished</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><code>mail_error.*</code> Used when sending notifications on
                            errors</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <para>In these templates you can see a number of keys (in the format of
                    <code>[KEYNAME]</code>)  with different names that are replaced with the actual
                values at the time the mail should be sent. The name of the keys should make it
                obvious what value they will be replaced with is.</para>
            <para>If you like to change the appearance of any of these templates, then by all means,
                go ahead !</para>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
            <title>Adding user "hooks" for special processing</title>
            <para>To maintain maximum flexibility the daemon will check for the existence of several
                (optional) shell scripts that can be provided by the user to take special actions on
                server shutdown, server startup, channel switching etc. The package provides
                templates for all of them that can be tweaked and then stored in the configuration
                directory (by default <filename>/etc/tvpvrd</filename>). The available hooks are
                listed below with a note if they are mandatory or not. To use the hooks they must
                first be renamed by removing the "<filename>*.template</filename>" extension. For
                the majority of the these script the daemon will call them with optional arguments.
                The template code shows how to make use fo these arguments, for example the full
                filename of a video that has just been recorded.</para>
            <para>After the list we give some examples on how these hooks can be used</para>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><filename>postrec_processing.sh.template</filename> , (<emphasis
                                role="italic">optional</emphasis>) This script is called just after
                            a recording has been done and before any (optional) transcoding is
                            taking place. The usage (or not) of this script is controlled in the
                            configuration <code>use_postrec_processing</code></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><filename>posttransc_processing.sh.template</filename> , (<emphasis
                                role="italic">optional</emphasis>) This script is called just after
                            a transcoding has been finished. The usage (or not) of this script is
                            controlled in the configuration
                            <code>use_posttransc_processing</code></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><filename>shutdown.sh.template</filename>, (<emphasis
                                role="italic">optional</emphasis>) This script is called when
                            automatic shutdown has been enabled (<code>shutdown::enable=yes</code>)
                            , By default it will just do a full system shutdown. This script is
                            mandatory if automatic shutdown has been enabled.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><filename>startup.sh.template</filename> , (<emphasis
                                role="italic">optional</emphasis>) This script is called right after
                            the daemon has started but before any recordings are started.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><filename>switchchannel.sh.template</filename>, (<emphasis
                                role="italic">optional</emphasis>) This script is called when the
                            channel should be changed. This is controlled in the configuration file
                                (<code>external_switch=yes</code>) </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <para>Some typical usages of  these hooks are:</para>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Handling automatic mounting/unmounting of filesystems. If the server
                            running the daemon have exported filesystems to allow clients to fetch
                            the videos by either SMB or NFS mounting there will be problem if those
                            filesystems are still mounted if the server initiates an automatic
                            shutdown. NFS is notoriously bad in handling a server no longer
                            available and it can cause hangs and freezes in the client when it waits
                            indefinitely for the server to respond. </para>
                        <para>This can be handled by allowing the recording server to execute
                            mounting/unmounting scripts on clients (via ssh). To allow ssh execution
                            without passwords the recording server must be allowed to access a
                            client via ssh and using public keys without passwords. This means that
                            the recording servers public key (<filename>id_rsa.pub</filename>) must
                            be stored in the clients "<filename>authorized_keys</filename>" file
                            (usually in the home directory under <filename>.ssh/</filename>)</para>
                        <para>In the shutdown script one has then to add calls to each client to
                            unmount the filesystems and in the startup script one can call the
                            clients to re-mount all the necessary filesystems.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If you have an external cable box connected to one of the fixed video
                            input on the card the card itself cannot change the channels since that
                            must be done on the cable box. The switchchannel script should be used
                            for this. By attaching a suitable Infrared transmitter on the server
                            which can be controlled in the switchchannel script the dameon can
                            control the channel on the cable box via this script. It is
                            unfortunately beyond the scope of this manual to describe how to setup
                            an infrared sender on a Linux server (see
                                <uri>http://www.lirc.org/</uri>for more information)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Some video cards require some postprocessing on the MP2 video before
                            it is transcoded to MP4, This postprocessing can be done in the
                                <filename>postrec_processing.sh</filename> script.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <para>Just remember to rename the templates by removing the
                    "<filename>*.template</filename>" extension so they can be found by the
                daemon.</para>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
            <title>Commands (in alphabetic order)</title>
            <para>The following is a list and detailed explanation of the commands that are
                recognized by the server. Commands are specified by 1 to 3 letters followed by any
                necessary arguments. It is possible to get more detailed help/information for each
                command by giving the help command 'h' followed by the command, e.g. 'h l', will
                give more detailed help on the 'list' command.</para>
            <para>Since there are quite a few commands we start with an overview with a one line
                explanation of each command. Further details can be found below</para>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">a</emphasis> - add new recording command</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">af</emphasis> - add recordings from file</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">ar</emphasis> - add new recurring recording</para>
                    </listitem>                    
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">d</emphasis> - delete single recording</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">df</emphasis> - display used disk space for data
                            directory</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">dp</emphasis> - display all settings for specified
                            profile</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">dr</emphasis> - delete all repeated recording </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">h</emphasis> - help</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">kt</emphasis> - kill all ongoing transcoding(s)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">ktf</emphasis> - set/unset kill transcoding flag at
                            shutdown</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">l [n]</emphasis> - list all pending recordings, possibly
                            restricted to the next &lt;n> recordings</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">lh [n]</emphasis> - list all pending record in a shorter
                            more human readable format</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">lc</emphasis> - list all controls for the capture
                            card</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">li [n]</emphasis> - list all input sources available for
                            the capture card</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">log &lt;n></emphasis> -show the last n lines of the
                            logfile</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">ls</emphasis> - list all stations</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">lp</emphasis> - list all profiles</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">lq &lt;n></emphasis> - list queued transcodings for
                            video card &lt;n></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">n</emphasis> - list the immediate next recording on each
                            video</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">o</emphasis> - list the ongoing recording(s)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">ot</emphasis> - list the ongoing transcoding(s)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">q</emphasis> - quick recording, start the recording
                            immediately and continue the specified time</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">rst</emphasis> - reset all statistics</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">rp</emphasis> - refresh transcoding profiles from
                            file</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">s</emphasis> - print server status</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">sp</emphasis> - set transcoding profile for specified
                            recording</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">st</emphasis> - print profile statistics</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">t</emphasis> - print server time</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">tf</emphasis> - transcode specified file</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">tl</emphasis> - read list of videos to transcode from
                            file</para>
                    </listitem>                    
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">td</emphasis> - transcode all videos in directory</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">u</emphasis> - force update of database with
                            recordings</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">v</emphasis> - print version</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">vc &lt;n></emphasis> - print information on TV-Card
                            &lt;n></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">wt</emphasis> - list waiting transcodings</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">x</emphasis> - view database (in XML format) with
                            recordings</para>
                    </listitem>                    
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">z</emphasis> - display all settings from ini-file</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">! &lt;n></emphasis> - cancel ongoing recording on video
                            card &lt;n></para>
                    </listitem>                    
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <para>The input and output has a format suitable for both human interactive use as well
                as a programatically interfacing the server in order to build a UI that interacts
                with the server.</para>

                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>a</command>' - <emphasis
                            role="bold">Add new recording command</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Add new recording. The date/time logic is fairly complete and will
                                for example correctly handle date crossings when recording starts
                                and ends on different sides on the midnight. For all recording
                                formats both title and profile might be omitted. In such case the
                                title will be constructed from the station/channel name and the
                                start date/time.</para>
                            <para>If no end time is given the recording will have the default
                                recording length as defined in the ini-file. In the distribution
                                this is set to 0:59 hours.</para>
                            <para>For all variants the start and end time is specified as</para>
                            <para>
                            <emphasis>hh</emphasis> [:<emphasis>mm</emphasis>[:<emphasis>ss</emphasis>]]
                            </para>
                            <para>The maximum length for one recording is 4 hours in order to keep
                                the file size manageable.</para>
                            <para>The primary formats are described below. The syntactic element
                                used have the following meaning:</para>
                            <para>&lt;<emphasis
                                    role="italic">ch</emphasis>> = Channel or station name</para>
                            <para>&lt;<emphasis
                                    role="italic">starttime</emphasis>> = Time for recording
                                start</para>
                            <para>&lt;<emphasis
                                    role="italic">endtime</emphasis>> = Time for recording
                                end</para>
                            <para>&lt;<emphasis
                                    role="italic">title</emphasis>> = Title of recording. This will
                                also be used as the filename of the resulting file. Note that the
                                filename will always be converted to lower case.</para>
                            <para>&lt;<emphasis
                                    role="italic">@profile</emphasis>> = Name of the profile(s) to
                                be used to the recording. Up to 4 profiles can be specified for each
                                recording.</para>
                            <para>The three main variants of the add command are:</para>

                            <para><emphasis>a &lt;ch> &lt;starttime> [&lt;title>]
                                [&lt;@profile]</emphasis></para>
                            
                            <para>Specification of only start time. The end time
                                will match the default recording length as specified
                                in the ini-file.</para>
                            <para>If the start time is after the current time the
                                date will be assumed to be today. If the time is
                                earlier than the current time the date is assumed to
                                be tomorrow.</para>
                            <para>If no title is specified the title will be
                                constructed from the station/channel name and the
                                start date and time.</para>
                            <para>If no profile is specified then the default
                                profile specified in the ini-file will be
                                used.</para>
                            
                            <para><emphasis>a &lt;ch> &lt;starttime> &lt;endtime>
                                [&lt;title>] [&lt;@profile]</emphasis></para>
                            
                            <para>Specification of both start and end time.</para>
                            <para>If the start time is after the current time the
                                date will be assumed to be today. If the time is
                                earlier than the current time the date is assumed to
                                be tomorrow.</para>
                            <para>If no title is specified the title will be
                                constructed from the station/channel name and the
                                start date and time.</para>
                            <para>If no profile is specified then the default
                                profile specified in the ini-file will be
                                used.</para>                            
                            
                            <para><emphasis>a &lt;ch> &lt;startdate> &lt;starttime>
                                &lt;endtime> [&lt;title>]
                                [&lt;@profile]</emphasis></para>
                            
                            <para>Full date and time specification. The date can be
                                specified as either a numeric ordinary date (note the order!):</para>

                                <para><emphasis>yyyy-mm-dd</emphasis></para>
                                <para>Numerical date yyyy=year, mm=month [1-12],dd=day [1-31]</para>
                            
                                <para>or as week day in the coming week relative from todays date</para>
                                                                
                                <para>[<emphasis>today</emphasis>|<emphasis>tomorrow</emphasis>|<emphasis>mon</emphasis>|<emphasis>tue</emphasis>|<emphasis>wed</emphasis>|<emphasis>thu</emphasis>|<emphasis>fri</emphasis>|<emphasis>sat</emphasis>|<emphasis>sun</emphasis>]</para>
                                <para>Relative date from today. The weekday name
                                    refers to the coming 7 days. If the same day as
                                    the current day is given then this refers to 7
                                    days in the future.</para>
                                                                
                            
                            <para>If the start time is after the current time the
                                date will be assumed to be today. If the time is
                                earlier than the current time the date is assumed to
                                be tomorrow.</para>
                            <para>If no title is specified the title will be
                                constructed from the station/channel name and the
                                start date and time.</para>
                            <para>If no profile is specified then the default
                                profile specified in the ini-file will be
                                used.</para>                                                        
                            
                            <para><emphasis
                                    role="bold">Examples</emphasis>:</para>
                            <screen>a bbc1 19:30</screen>
                            <para>Start a recording at 19:30 on station BBC1 which will have the
                                default duration, default title and profile. </para>
                            <screen>a bbc1 tue 19:30 News</screen>
                            <para>Start a recording at 19:30 on station BBC1 the coming Tuesday
                                which will have the default duration with title 'News' and profile. </para>
                            <screen>a bbc1 19:30 21:15 News </screen>
                            <para>Start a recording at 19:30 which will last until 21:15 on BBC1
                                with title set to "News". The default profile will be used. </para>
                            <screen>a ch4 wed 22:00 23:45 The Movie </screen>
                            <para>Start a recording the coming Wednesday at 22:00 until 23:45 on CH4
                                with title "The Movie". The default profile will be used. </para>
                            <screen>a bbc2 tomorrow 18 20 "World in Focus" @mobile </screen>
                            <para>Start a recording tomorrow at 18:00 until 20:00 on bbc2 with title
                                "World in Focus". Using the mobile profile.</para>
                            <screen>a bbc2 tomorrow 18 20 "World in Focus" @mobile @normal</screen>
                            <para>Start a recording tomorrow at 18:00 until 20:00 on bbc2 with title
                                "World in Focus". Using both the mobile and the normal profile.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>'<command>af</command>
                        <emphasis
                            role="italic">&lt;filename></emphasis>' - <emphasis
                            role="bold">Add recordings from file</emphasis></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Add recordings (specified with either the '<emphasis
                                role="bold">a</emphasis>' or the '<emphasis
                                role="bold">ar</emphasis>' command) from a file. The file is simply
                            a list with one command per line that is formatted exactly as if the
                            command would have been entered in the teminal directly. The purpose of
                            this is primarily to allow other programs to generate a list of future
                            recordings that can be easily added to the daemon.</para>
                        <para>The filename specified must be give as a full path filename since the
                            daemon has no concept of a current directory.</para>
                        <para><emphasis
                                role="bold">Example:</emphasis></para>
                        <para>
                            <screen>af /tmp/newrecs.txt</screen>
                        </para>
                        <para>The file <filename>/tmp/newrecs.txt</filename> could then have the
                            following lines (for example)</para>
                        <para>
                            <screen>a ch4 21:00 21:59 Child of our time @thigh
a bbc1 20:00 20:59 Walking with dinosaurs
a bbb1 21:00 21:29 lastnews @tlow</screen>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>ar</command>' - <emphasis
                                role="bold">Add recurring recording command</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Add a new repeated recording . The syntax is identical to the
                                normal add command with the exception of the first two arguments
                                which indicates the type of recurrence and the number of repeated
                                occurrences or the end date. The full syntax is</para>
                            <para><emphasis>ar &lt;repeat-type> &lt;repeat-count | end-date> &lt;normal add arguments></emphasis></para>
                            <para><emphasis>repeat-type</emphasis></para>
                            <para>This specifies how often the repetition should be
                                done. This can be specified as one of the following
                                arguments:</para>

                            <para>'<option>d</option>' - Repeat daily (can
                                also be specified as '1')</para>
                            
                            
                            <para>'<option>w</option>' - Repeat weekly (can
                                also be specified as '2')</para>
                            
                            
                            <para>'<option>m</option>' - Repeat monthly (can
                                also be specified as '3')</para>
                            
                            
                            <para>'<option>f</option>' - Repeat Monday to
                                Friday (can also be specified as '4')</para>
                            
                            
                            <para>'<option>s</option>' - Repeat every Saturday
                                to Sunday (can also be specified as '5')</para>
                            
                            
                            <para>'<option>t</option>' - Repeat every Monday
                                to Thursday (can also be specified as '6')</para>
                                                        
                            <para><emphasis>repeat-cnt | end-date</emphasis></para>
                            <para>This specifies the number of repeated recordings
                                by either specifying the number of repeats (as an
                                integer) or by specifying the end date. If an end
                                date is specified this includes the full final day
                                up to 23:59:59</para>
                            <para>Since only one title is given for multiple recording the titles
                                will be mangled with the recording date and time. In the recording
                                list the title will usually be shown as "Base title (xx/yy)" where
                                xx is the sequence number and yy is the total number of recordings
                                in this sequence.</para>
                        <para>By default a series of recordings specified with this command is
                            stored under a subdirectory with the same name as the basename of the
                            recording. If you instead prefer to have all recordings stored in a flat
                            structure directly under the recordings directory then set the config
                            setting (in the config file) '<code>use_repeat_rec_basedir</code>' to
                                '<code>no</code>'.</para>
                            <para><emphasis
                                    role="bold">Examples:</emphasis></para>
                            <screen>ar f 10 bbc1 18 18:30 News</screen>
                            <para>Start recording every Mon-Tue at BBC1 between 18:00 and
                                18:30</para>
                            <screen>ar w 20 tv1 tue 21:15 22:10 John Adams</screen>
                            <para>Start a recording once a week on Tuesday evening at 21:15 until
                                22:10 with base title "John Adams". </para>
                            <screen>ar s 10 BBC1 01:00 02:30 Night movie </screen>
                            <para>Add a recording every weekend night between 01:00 and 02:30 with
                                the base title "Night movie". The recording will be done for the
                                next 5 weekends (2 recordings each weekend).</para>
                            <screen>ar t 2010-05-10 channel3 19:00 19:59 House</screen>
                            <para>This will make recordings every Mon-Thur at 19:00 until the 10:th
                                of May 2010</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>d</command>
                            <emphasis>nnn</emphasis>' - <emphasis
                                role="bold">Delete specified recording</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Delete specified recording. <emphasis>nnn</emphasis> is the
                                recoding id shown when a recording is added or by the list command.
                                If the identified recording is part of a recurrent sequence the
                                other recordings in the same sequence are untouched.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>'<command>df</command>' - <emphasis
                            role="bold">Display total and used disk space</emphasis></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Displays in both absolute and relative terms the amount of disk space
                            on the partition containing the specified data directory (as specified
                            in the config file). The size is given in "human" readable format which
                            means the use of M = Megabyte, G = Gigabyte and T = Terabyte. </para>
                        <para>Output example:</para>
                        <para>
                            <screen>612G of 4,1T (15 percent used) </screen>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>dp</command> [<emphasis>@profile</emphasis>]' - Display
                            profile information command</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Display information on the settings of the specified profile. </para>
                            <para>Output example:</para>
                            <screen>name                  : normal
ENCODER:
video_bitrate         : 3700000
video_peak_bitrate    : 4700000
audio_sampling        : 44.1
audio_bitrate         : 192
aspect                : 4x3
size                  : pal
FFMPEG:
use_transcoding       : 0
video_bitrate         : 800
video_peak_bitrate    : 1100
vcodec                : libx264
vpre                  : medium
pass                  : 1
acodec                : libfaac
audio_bitrate         : 128
video_size            : 
crop                  : l=0, r=0, t=0, b=0
ffmpeg_extra_options  : 
file_extension        : .mp4</screen>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>dr</command>
                            <emphasis>nnn</emphasis>' - <emphasis
                                role="bold">Delete all repeated recordings</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Delete all repeated recording that are part of the same repeating
                                sequence as the id of the recording specified.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>exit</command> - <emphasis
                                role="bold">Disconnect from the server</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>This command terminates the client connection to the server. It
                                will not affect any of the ongoing recordings or
                                transcodings.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>h</command>' - <emphasis
                                role="bold">Help command</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Print a summary of all commands available.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>kt</command>' <emphasis
                            role="italic">n</emphasis> - <emphasis
                            role="bold">Kill all ongoing transcoding command</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Stop specified ongoing transcoding processes. The index of the
                            ongoing transcoding processes can be found via the <command>ot</command>
                            command. If no specific index is given then all ongoing transcodings
                            will be stopped so be careful !</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>ktf</command>
                            [<emphasis>y</emphasis>|<emphasis>n</emphasis>]' - <emphasis
                                role="bold">Kill transcoding flag set/unset
                            command</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The kill transcoding flag determines whether or not the
                                transcoding processes should be killed when the server is stopped.
                                By default all transcoding processes are killed when the tvpvrd
                                server is killed. By setting this flag to 'n' (No) the transcoding
                                processes will be allowed to keep running after the server is
                                stopped.</para>
                            <para>Output example:</para>
                            <screen>ktf n
killflag=n</screen>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>l</command>' <emphasis
                            role="italic">n</emphasis> - <emphasis
                            role="bold">List future recordings command</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>List coming recordings. If  <emphasis
                                role="italic">n</emphasis> is specified as number in the range
                            [1,99] then the list will be limited to <emphasis
                                role="italic">n</emphasis> recordings. Otherwise all pending
                            recordings will be listed.</para>
                            <para>Each record is listed with 7 fields. Each record starts with a '['
                                and ends with a ']' character. Each field is separated with a bar
                                '|'. The order of fields are</para>
                            <para>
                                <screen>&lt;id#> &lt;station/channel name> &lt;start-date> &lt;start-time> &lt;end-time> &lt;title> &lt;profile></screen>
                            </para>
                            <para>Output example:</para>
                            <screen>[160|tv4    |2010-03-09|21:00|21:59|House (16/20)                 |@normal]
[135|kanal5 |2010-03-11|21:00|21:59|Criminal minds (16/20)        |@normal]
[038|kanal5 |2010-03-11|22:00|22:59|Fringe (17/20)                |@normal]
[088|kanal5 |2010-03-14|22:25|23:19|Supernatural (18/21)          |@normal]
[161|tv4    |2010-03-16|21:00|21:59|House (17/20)                 |@normal]
[136|kanal5 |2010-03-18|21:00|21:59|Criminal minds (17/20)        |@normal]
[039|kanal5 |2010-03-18|22:00|22:59|Fringe (18/20)                |@normal]</screen>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>'<command>lh</command>' [<emphasis>n</emphasis>] - <emphasis
                            role="bold">List future recordings in human readable
                        format</emphasis></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>This is the same command as 'l' but with the output shortened and ore
                            easily read by humans</para>
                        <para>Output example:</para>
                        <screen>Fri Oct 01 21:00-21:55 disc     Mountains
Fri Oct 01 22:05-23:15 bbc1     Changes</screen>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>log</command>' [<emphasis>n</emphasis>] - <emphasis
                                role="bold">Show last n lines of the log file</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>If the logfile has been specified as a file (in
                                    <filename>tvpvrd.conf</filename>) then this command will show
                                the last n lines of the log. If no number is given it will default
                                to show the last 10 lines. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>li</command> [<emphasis
                            role="italic">n</emphasis>] - <emphasis
                            role="bold">List all video input sources command</emphasis></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>List a all video sources available for the specified card. The current
                            selected input source is marked with an asterisk. The type of input is
                            shown in parenthesis in front of the textual name of the input. The type
                            is either "tuner" or "camera". If no card is specified then information
                            on all installed card will be listed.</para>
                        <para>Output example:</para>
                        
                            <screen>Hauppauge WinTV PVR-350 
00 :*(tuner) Tuner 1 
01 : (camera) S-Video 1 
02 : (camera) Composite 1 
03 : (camera) S-Video 2 
04 : (camera) Composite 2 
05 : (camera) Composite 3 </screen>
                        
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>lp</command>' - <emphasis
                                role="bold">List profiles command</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Print a list of all defined transcoding profiles numbered one per
                            line(use '<command>dp</command>' command to display details of a
                            specified profile)</para>
                        <para>Output example:</para>
                        <screen>#01 : mobile
#02 : low
#03 : cropnormal
#04 : tnormal
#05 : high
#06 : normal
#07 : wnormal</screen>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>ls</command>' - <emphasis
                                role="bold">List stations command</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>List all defined station names. The stations are specified in the
                                    <filename>xawtvrc</filename> file and maps station names to
                                channel names. When defining the frequency for a recording either
                                the defined station name or channel (frequency) name can be
                                used.</para>
                            <para>Output example:</para>
                            <screen>SE11: kanal5
  57: kanal8
 S36: kanal9
SE16: mtv
 E10: svt24
SE13: svtb/kunsk
  E5: tv1
  E7: tv2
 E11: tv3
  E6: tv4
SE14: tv4+
  E8: tv6</screen>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>lc</command> [<emphasis>#card</emphasis>]' - <emphasis
                                role="bold">List all video capture card controls
                            command</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>This can be considered a low level command of limited use for an
                            end user. This command will list all user controllable video/audio
                            controls that can be adjusted on the specified video card. This is
                            directly related to the discovered 'v4l2' interfaces. Since the output
                            is quite long we do not include any example output here. The output is
                            intentionally modeled to be of the same format as the one used in 'v4l2'
                            output.</para>
                            <para>(This command is probably of little use for anything else than
                                troubleshooting a video card and driver.)</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>lq</command> [<emphasis>#filelist</emphasis>]' - <emphasis
                                role="bold">List information on the ongoing transcoding of file list <emphasis
                                    role="italic">#filelist</emphasis></emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>List some useful information on the specified transcoding file
                                list. The transcoding file list is a list with filenames that are
                                queued up for transcoding. A transcoding file list is added with the <emphasis
                                    role="bold">tr</emphasis> command. Up to five simultaneous lists
                                may be added. However, since transcoding is such a heavy job there
                                is little real reason to add more than one lists at a time since a
                                list with, say 20 full length movie video files, can easily take up
                                more than two days to transcode.</para>
                            <para>Output example:</para>
                            
                                <screen>       Filelist: #01                                
          Total: 17 videos in list                  
      Processed: 02 (11%) files                     
    Job started: Mon Jan 25 16:29:53 2010           
   Running time: 00 days 00:14 h                    
 Est. time left: -1 days ~-1 h (approx.)            
                                    
Processed:
  * /data/pvr/mp2/normal/svu_001.mpg
  * /data/pvr/mp2/normal/svu_2010-01-20_00.40.mpg
                                    
Not processed:
  + /data/pvr/mp2/normal/svu_2010-01-21_00.40.mpg
  + /data/pvr/mp2/normal/svu_2010-01-22_00.40.mpg
  + /data/pvr/mp2/normal/svu2ggr.mpg             
  + /data/pvr/mp2/normal/svu_k9_001.mpg          
  + /data/pvr/mp2/normal/svu-k9_2010-01-21_00.05.mpg
  + /data/pvr/mp2/normal/svu-k9_2010-01-22_00.05.mpg
  + /data/pvr/mp2/normal/svu.mpg                    
  + /data/pvr/mp2/normal/two_and_half_men_001.mpg   
  + /data/pvr/mp2/normal/two_and_half_men_002.mpg   
  + /data/pvr/mp2/normal/two_and_half_men.mpg       
  + /data/pvr/mp2/normal/vrldens_undergng.mpg     
  + /data/pvr/mp2/normal/vita_huset_001.mpg         
  + /data/pvr/mp2/normal/vita_huset.mpg             
  + /data/pvr/mp2/normal/white_noise.mpg            
  + /data/pvr/mp2/normal/WildThings.mpg  </screen>
                            
                            <para>The fist set of information gives general information about the
                                chosen file list. The last line of the first information block gives
                                a rough estimate of the remaining time left needed to transcode the
                                list. This is a very approximate estimation based on the time it has
                                taken to transcode the files in the list up to now. In the example
                                above the estimate is shown as -1 indicating that there are too few
                                completed transcodings for any estimate to be done. At least 2
                                transcoding must have been completed in order for the estimate to be
                                shown.</para>
                            <para>The next set of information is the "<code>Processed:</code>"
                                files. This is the files that have been processed, meaning it has
                                been submitted for transcoding. This means that they have either
                                been completely transcoded or is in the process of being
                                transcoded.</para>
                            <para>The final block of information, the "<code>Not processed:</code>"
                                block is the remainder of the files which are still waiting to be
                                processed. No files are submitted for processing until the system
                                load has fallen below the maximum limit for transcoding to start as
                                specified in the <filename>tvpvrd.conf</filename> file.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>n</command>' - <emphasis
                                role="bold">Next recording command</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>List the immediate next recording(s) scheduled for the available
                                video card(s). The first number in parenthesis is how long time
                                until the recording will start.</para>
                            <para>Output example:</para>
                            <screen>(01:37) : [002|tv3    |2009-11-20|18:00|18:59|NCIS_18 (02/20)               |@normal]
(52:37) : [143|tv4    |2009-11-22|21:00|22:00|Shooter 1                     |@normal]</screen>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>o</command>' - <emphasis
                                role="bold">Ongoing recordings command</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>List all ongoing recording in ordinary list format for all video
                                cards. If no recordings are ongoing the output will show
                                "None"</para>
                            <para>Output example:</para>
                            <screen>Video #0: [175|tv1    |2009-11-20|16:26|16:27|tv1_20091120_1626             |@normal]
Video #1: None.</screen>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>ot</command>' - <emphasis
                                role="bold">Ongoing transcodings command</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>List all ongoing transcodings. The output format is</para>
                            <para>
                                <screen>&lt;#id> &lt;start-time> &lt;(duration)> &lt;filename> &lt;profile></screen>
                            </para>
                            <para>The start time identifies when the transcoding was started and
                                duration shows for how long the transcoding has been running.</para>
                            <para>Output example:</para>
                            <screen>[#00|16:27|(00:00)|tv1_20091120_1626.mpg              |normal]</screen>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>otl</command>' - <emphasis
                                role="bold">Ongoing transcoding long command</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>List all ongoing transcoding in long format which includes the
                                detailed 'ffmpeg' command used which is printed on the second
                                line.</para>
                            <para>Output example:</para>
                            <screen>[#00|16:27|(00:00)|tv1_20091120_1626.mpg              |normal]
(cmd: /usr/bin/ffmpeg -v 0 -i tv1_20091120_1626.mpg -threads 0 
-vcodec libx264 -vpre normal -b 700k -bt 1000k  -croptop 8 -cropbottom 8 
-cropleft 2 -cropright 2  -acodec copy -ab 196k  -y  
tv1_20091120_1626.mp4 > /dev/null 2>&amp;1)</screen>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>q</command>' - <emphasis
                                role="bold">Quick recording command</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Add new recording that will start immediately. This is basically
                            the same as a simplified '<command>a</command>' command where the start
                            time and start date is always the current date and time.</para>
                            <para>The format of the command are</para>
                            <para>
                                <variablelist>
                                    <varlistentry>
                                        <term><emphasis>q &lt;ch> [&lt;duration>] [&lt;title>]
                                                [&lt;@profile]</emphasis></term>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>The recording will start within a few seconds
                                                (depending on the resolution time specified in the
                                                ini-file) and will last for the duration specified.
                                                If no duration is specified the default duration
                                                time will be used. The duration is specified with
                                                hours and minutes as</para>
                                            <para><emphasis>hh:mm</emphasis></para>
                                            <para>If no title is specified the title will be
                                            constructed from the station/channel name and the start
                                            date and time. </para>
                                            <para>If no profile is specified then the default
                                                profile specified in the ini-file will be used.
                                            </para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </varlistentry>
                                </variablelist>
                            </para>
                            <para><emphasis
                                    role="bold">Examples</emphasis>:</para>
                            <screen>q bbc2  </screen>
                            <para>Start a recording immediately on bbc2 using the default duration,
                                title and profile.</para>
                            <screen>q bbc2 1:30 </screen>
                            <para>Start a recording immediately on bbc2 with duration 1 hour 30
                                minutes, using default title and default profile. </para>
                            <screen>q bbc2 News </screen>
                            <para>Start a recording immediately on bbc2 with default duration using
                                the title "News" and default profile.</para>
                            <screen>q ch4 1:45 Newsfocus @high  </screen>
                            <para>Start a new recording on station 'ch4' with title 'Newsfocus'
                                using the 'high' profile. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>rst</command>' - <emphasis
                                role="bold">Reset statistics command</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Reset all statistics, i.e. set all statistics to 0.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>rp</command>' - <emphasis
                                role="bold">Refresh profiles command</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>This command will cause the profiles to be re-read from profile
                                files. This can be used to refresh the profiles without having to
                                restart the server.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>sp</command>
                            <emphasis>nnn</emphasis>
                            <emphasis>@profile</emphasis>' - <emphasis
                                role="bold">Set profile command</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Specify the profiles to be used on the specified recording. This
                                will replace any previous defined profiles for this recording. Up to
                                four profiles per recording can be defined.</para>
                            <para><emphasis
                                    role="bold">Examples:</emphasis></para>
                            <screen>sp 87 @normal @mobile</screen>
                            <para>Use profiles <emphasis>normal</emphasis> and
                                    <emphasis>mobile</emphasis> for recording
                                    <emphasis>#87</emphasis></para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>s</command>' - <emphasis
                                role="bold">Server status command</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Print a summary of the server status. This includes information on
                                when the tvpvrd was started, how long it has been running for, the
                                current server load, current server time, allocated virtual memory,
                                number of running threads in the server and finally a list of
                                clients currently connected to the server.</para>
                            <para>Output example:</para>
                            <screen>Current time    : Sun Oct 10 09:48:24 2010
tvpvrd started  : Fri Oct  8 08:53:00 2010
tvpvrd uptime   : 02 days 00 hours 55 min
Server uptime   : 03 days 02 hours 37 min
Server load     : 0.1 0.1 0.0
Virtual memory  : 56796 kB
Threads         : 4
Clients         : #01: 192.168.0.31, Sun Oct 10 09:48:24 2010</screen>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>st</command>' - <emphasis
                                role="bold">Print profile statistics</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Print transcoding statistics for the defined profiles. This
                            statistics is gathered for every transcoding made. The statistics
                            includes among other things the running time and average size per minute
                            of the original MP2 and the transcoded file. The statistics for the
                            transcoding can be used to predict how long time a transcoding will
                            take. However since it is highly dependent on the load on the server it
                            can be difficult to accurately predict the needed transcoding time. </para>
                            <para>Output example:</para>
                            <screen>profile_name            : 'normal'
transcoding_speed       : 44 s transcoded / min
mp2size_1min            : 27.5 Mb/min
mp4size_1min            : 6.4 Mb/min
comp_ratio              : 4.3
total_ttime             : 3481 min
total_mp2time           : 1779 min
total_mp2files          : 31
total_mp4files          : 31</screen>
                            <para>The different fields have the following meaning</para>
                            <para>
                                <variablelist>
                                    <varlistentry>
                                        <term><emphasis>profile_name</emphasis></term>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>The name of the profile that this statistics apply
                                                to.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </varlistentry>
                                    <varlistentry>
                                        <term><emphasis>transcoding_speed</emphasis></term>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>How much play time the server on average can
                                                transcode per minute run time of 'ffmpeg'.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </varlistentry>
                                    <varlistentry>
                                        <term><emphasis>mp2size_1min</emphasis></term>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>The average size of 1 minute play time in the
                                                original MP2 file.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </varlistentry>
                                    <varlistentry>
                                        <term><emphasis>mp4size_1min</emphasis></term>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>The average size of 1 minute of play time in the
                                                resulting transcoded MP4 size.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </varlistentry>
                                    <varlistentry>
                                        <term><emphasis>comp_ratio</emphasis></term>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>The compression ration between the original MP2
                                                size and the MP4 transcoded file.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </varlistentry>
                                    <varlistentry>
                                        <term><emphasis>total_ttime</emphasis></term>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>Total running time that has been spent transcoding
                                                files.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </varlistentry>
                                    <varlistentry>
                                        <term><emphasis>total_mp2time</emphasis></term>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>Total recorded original MP2 time.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </varlistentry>
                                    <varlistentry>
                                        <term><emphasis>total_mp2files</emphasis></term>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>Total number of mp2files recorded with this
                                                profile.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </varlistentry>
                                    <varlistentry>
                                        <term><emphasis>total_mp4files</emphasis></term>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>Total number of transcoded MP4 files with this
                                                profile.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </varlistentry>
                                </variablelist>
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>t</command>' - <emphasis
                                role="bold">Current Time and Date command</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Print current time and date on the server where 'tvpvrd' is
                                running</para>
                            <para>Output example:</para>
                            <screen>Fri Nov 20 15:51:20 2009</screen>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>tf</command>
                            <emphasis>filename</emphasis> [<emphasis>@profile</emphasis>]' - <emphasis
                                role="bold">Transcode specified file using the named optional
                                profile</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>This command is used to transcode any file within the file system
                                using a specified transcoding profile. If the profile name is not
                                given the the system default transcoding profile will be
                                used.</para>
                            <para>filename is the full path to the (normally MP2) video file that
                                should be encoded. The resulting transcoded file is stored in the
                                    <filename>&lt;datadir>/mp4/&lt;profile>/</filename> directory.
                                During the transcoding a temporary directory under
                                    <filename>&lt;datadir>/vtmp/</filename> is created and used as a
                                working directory. The original file is not chnaged in any ways.
                                During the transcoding a symbolic link is created in the temporary
                                directory which makes it in theory possible to have the original
                                file on another file system.</para>
                            <para>Example</para>
                            <para>
                                <screen>tf /data/pvr/mp2/normal/oldreccording.mpg @high</screen>
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>tl</command>
                            <emphasis>filename</emphasis> [<emphasis>@profile</emphasis>]' - <emphasis
                                role="bold">Queue all files listed in file <emphasis
                                    role="italic">filename</emphasis> for transcoding using the
                                named optional profile</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>This commands will queue all (video) files listed in the file
                                specified in the command for transcoding. </para>
                            <para>The list file consists of a number of lines (each line ending with
                                a newline) with either</para>


                                        <para>a fully specified video file name or</para>
                                    

                                        <para>a filepath which will be used for the following files
                                            as prefix until the next filepath is specified. A
                                            filepath is identified by having the first character on
                                            the row being a ':' (colon) character.</para>
                                    
                            <para>Example input file:</para>
                            
                                <programlisting>:/data/pvr/mp2/normal
svu_001.mpg
svu_2010-01-20_00.40.mpg
svu_2010-01-21_00.40.mpg
svu_2010-01-22_00.40.mpg
svu2ggr.mpg
svu_k9_001.mpg
svu-k9_2010-01-21_00.05.mpg
svu-k9_2010-01-22_00.05.mpg
svu.mpg
two_and_half_men_001.mpg
two_and_half_men_002.mpg
two_and_half_men.mpg
vita_huset_001.mpg
vita_huset.mpg
white_noise.mpg
WildThings.mpg </programlisting>
                            
                            <para>In the above file all the video files will be read from the
                                directory <filename>/data/pvr/mp2/normal</filename>. The result of
                                the transcoding will (as usual) be stored under the corresponding
                                mp4 profile directory. Up to 5 different file lists can be added
                                simultaneous. There is no guarantee that files from all queued file
                                lists will be fairly processed, i.e. one file from the first list,
                                and when that is done, a file from the second file lists and so on.
                                This is completely random. The only thing that is guaranteed is that
                                the video files in each file lists will be processed
                                sequentially.</para>
                            <para>Remember that transcoding multiple files can take a long time. For
                                example a file list with 10 video files can easily take ~2 days (~4
                                hours transcoding time per video).</para>
                            <para>To view the status of ongoing list transcodings the "<emphasis
                                    role="bold">lq</emphasis>" (list-queue) command can be
                                used.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>td</command>
                            <emphasis>directory</emphasis> [<emphasis>@profile</emphasis>]' - <emphasis
                                role="bold">Transcode all files in the specified
                                directory</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>This command will search the specified directory for files with
                                recognized video suffix and submit all found files to
                                transcoding.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>u</command>' - <emphasis
                                role="bold">Update database file command</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Force update of the database file from memory. Normally this
                            command is not necessary since in versions above v1.2 of tvpvrd the
                            database is automatically updated whenever a new recording is added or
                            removed. This command is kept for backwards compatibility but should not
                            be used.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>v</command>' - <emphasis
                                role="bold">Version command</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Print program version and name as well as the build date. The
                                following lines will give information on how the server was
                                compiled.</para>
                            <para>Output example:</para>
                            <screen>tvpvrd 1.1.2 [client] (Jan 26 2010)
Compiled with Large File Support (files > 2GB).</screen>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>vc</command>
                                [<emphasis>0</emphasis>|<emphasis>1</emphasis>|<emphasis>2</emphasis>|<emphasis>3</emphasis>|<emphasis>4</emphasis>]'
                            - <emphasis
                                role="bold">Video Card information command</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Print information on the specified video/capture cards. The
                                command will print information of all available cards if no specific
                                card number is specified. The information shown is the name of the
                                card, driver and driver version.</para>
                            <para>Output example:</para>
                            <screen>Card 00: Hauppauge WinTV PVR-350, driver=ivtv v1.4.1
Card 01: Hauppauge WinTV PVR-150, driver=ivtv v1.4.1</screen>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>wt</command>' - <emphasis
                                role="bold">List all transcoding waiting to start</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>A transcoding is not started until the server load is below the
                                specified treshold in the ini-file. By default this treshold is 4.
                                This command will generate a list of all transcoding that are
                                waiting..</para>
                            <para>The listing uses the same format as the <command>ot</command>
                            command and contains (in order from left to right)</para>
                                <para>1. Sequence number</para>
                                <para>2. Time when item was enqueued</para>
                                <para>3. How long (hh:mm) the item has been waiting to be
                                    transcoded</para>
                                <para>4. Name of video file to be transcoded</para>
                                <para>5. Profile name to be used for the transcoding</para>
                            <para><emphasis
                                    role="bold">Note:</emphasis> There is no guarantee that the
                                files will be transcoded in the order indicated by the list.. </para>
                            <para>Output example:</para>
                            <screen>[#01|21:37|(00:04)|news_at_eight.mpg                          |@tnormal]
[#02|21:38|(00:03)|commander.mpg                              |@tnormal]</screen>                           
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>x</command>' - <emphasis
                                role="bold">View XML database command</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>View the current specified recordings in raw XML DB format. See <citerefentry>
                                    <refentrytitle>tvpvrd</refentrytitle>
                                    <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
                                </citerefentry> for details about the format.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>z</command>' - <emphasis
                            role="bold">Display all ini-file settings command</emphasis></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>This will list all settings made in the ini-file as well as the
                                location of the used ini file.</para>
                            <para>Output example:</para>
                            <screen>datadir                       : /data/pvr                    
use_profile_directories       : 0
use_repeat_rec_basedir        : 1                            
logfile                       : /tmp/tvpvrd.log              
verbose_log                   : 3                            
inifile_name                  : /etc/tvpvrd/tvpvrd.conf      
sendmail_on_error             : 1                            
sendmail_on_transcode_end     : 1                            
sendmail_on_shutdown          : 1                            
sendmail_address              : johan162@gmail.com           
locale_name                   : sv_SE.UTF8                   
smtp_use                      : 1                            
use_html                      : 1                            
smtp_server                   : 192.168.0.31                 
smtp_user                     : ljp                          
daemonize                     : 1                            
enable_webinterface           : 1                            
require_web_password          : 1                            
web_user                      : ljp
web_password                  : samba23
weblogin_timeout              : 0
username                      : root
xmldbfile_name                : /data/pvr/xmldb/tvpvrd_db.xml
max_video                     : 2
max_entries                   : 1024
max_clients                   : 4
client_idle_time              : 1800
port                          : 9300
time_resolution               : 3
video_buffer_size             : 307200 (0.3MB)
default_recording_time        : 00:59 (h:min)
xawtv_station file            : /etc/X11/xawtvrc
default_profile               : tnormal
frequency_map                 : europe-west
allow_profiles_adj_encoder    : 1
external_switch               : 0
external_input                : 1
external_switch_script        : switchchannel.sh
use_postrec_processing        : 1
postrec_processing_script     : postrec_processing.sh
shutdown_enable               : 1
shutdown_min_time             : 180
shutdown_ignore_users         : 0
shutdown_min_uptime           : 180
shutdown_pre_startup_time     : 180
shutdown_script_name          : shutdown.sh
</screen>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>'<command>!</command> [<emphasis>#videocard</emphasis>]' - Stop
                            recording on specified video card</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Stop the recording on the specified video card. The aborted
                                recording will be left in the '&lt;data-dir>/vtmp/vid&lt;n>/'
                                directory and must be manually removed. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1
            xml:id="tvpvrd.files">
            <title>Files</title>
            <para>Note: The system configuration directory to be used is a compile time settings and
                specified with the '<emphasis>configuration</emphasis>' argument '--sysconfdir'. </para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>/etc/X11/xawtvrc</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A list in ini-file format which maps the commonly known station name
                            to a frequency channel. This is the default location used by the package
                            xawtv</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>&lt;log-directory>/tvpvrd.log</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The logfile. The log-directory is specified in the ini-file. It can
                            also be specified as a command line argument (<option>-l,
                                --logfile</option>) which will then override the ini-file setting.
                            By default the log file will be stored under
                                <filename>/tmp/tvpvrd.log</filename> .(The reason not to use
                                <filename>/var/log/tvpvrd.log</filename> is the fact that the server
                            will not normally run as root and hence will not have write access to
                            this directory.)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>/var/run/tvpvrd.pid</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The pid of the started 'tvpvrd' server. This is used to easily find
                            the pid in order to shutdown the server. This is used by the
                                <emphasis>stop-tvpvrd</emphasis> script. Note that in order to use
                            this directory the daemon has to be started by the root user. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>/etc/tvpvrd/tvpvrd.conf</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Default configuration file</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>/etc/tvpvrd/profiles/</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Directory with all profiles</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>&lt;data-directory>/</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Directory where all recordings and temporary files are stored. The
                            root directory is specified in the configuration file. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>&lt;data-directory>/vtmp</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Video temporary directory. Used to store ongoing recordings and as
                            working directories while doing transcoding</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>&lt;data-directory>/mp2</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If the profile specifies that the original mp2 files should be kept
                            they are stored in this directory.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>&lt;data-directory>/mp4</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The transcoded files are stored under this folder in a subfolder with
                            the name of the profile used for the transcoding.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>&lt;data-directory>/xmldb</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The database file are stored under this directory. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>&lt;data-directory>/stats</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The statistics for each profile is stored in a file in XML format with
                            the same name as the profile and with the suffix '.stats'.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
            <title>Limitations</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Numerical dates must be specified in European format,
                            yyyy-mm-dd</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Not all international defined frequency maps are included. As of this
                            writing the following maps is not yet defined in the distribution.<itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>us-cable-hrc</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>us-cable-irc</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>japan-bcast</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>japan-cable</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>china-bcast</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>southafrica</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>argentina</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>australia-optus</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist></para>
                        <para>Frequency maps are a simple vector defining the frequency as an
                            integer and a string that defines the channel name. This is a compile
                            time setting and adding new maps will require recompilation of the
                            server. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The <filename>/var/run/tvpvrd.pid</filename> file is not removed after
                            the program has shut down if the effective user is any other than
                            'root', (by default the server will switch to the 'tvpvrd' user) since
                            only root has access to <filename>/var/run</filename></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Maximum recording time is 4 hours (in order to keep maximum MPEG2 file
                            size manageable). This can result in up to ~8GB MPEG2 files depending on
                            the HW bitrate used.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>All information and error messages are hard coded in English and
                            cannot be easily localized.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The server assumes that all installed capture cards uses the same
                            index to specify the tuner as input among all the possible input sources
                            (as specified by the configuration file setting
                                <emphasis>tuner_input_index</emphasis>)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
            <title>Bugs</title>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The configuration file has too many settings. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Theoretically if the server is extremely busy some newer recorded files
                        could be transcoded before older recordings. This is due to the fact that
                        there is not a central queue for the transcodings. Each recording just backs
                        off and waits a (random) time until it tries to see if it can start the
                        transcoding (when the server load is below the set threshold).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The '<command>i</command>' command is not yet implemented.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
            <title>Notes</title>
            <para>Any errors that are discovered in the startup phase before a logfile has been
                established will be written to the default system log (normally
                    <filename>/var/log/messages</filename>) </para>
            <para>The formal grammar for the XML based DB file is specified as an RNG (Relax New
                Grammar) XML specification included in the distribution in the docs
                directory.</para>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
            <title>Resources</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>SourceForge: &lt;http://sourceforge.net/projects/tvpvrd/></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>ivtv-driver: &lt;http://ivtvdriver.org/></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Video for Linux: &lt;http://linux.bytesex.org/v4l2/></para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
            <title>Author</title>
            <para>Written and maintained by Johan Persson &lt;johan162@gmail.com></para>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
            <title>Copyright</title>
            <para>Free use of this software is granted under the terms of the GNU General Public
                License (GPL v3)., see the file COPYING included in the distribution archive for
                details.</para>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1
            xml:id="tvpvrd.seealso">
            <title>See also</title>
            <para><citerefentry>
                    <refentrytitle>tvpowerd</refentrytitle>
                    <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
                </citerefentry>, <citerefentry>
                    <refentrytitle>ffmpeg</refentrytitle>
                    <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
                </citerefentry>, <citerefentry>
                    <refentrytitle>scantv</refentrytitle>
                    <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
                </citerefentry>, <citerefentry>
                    <refentrytitle>v4l-info</refentrytitle>
                    <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
                </citerefentry>, <citerefentry>
                    <refentrytitle>v4l-conf</refentrytitle>
                    <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
                </citerefentry>, <citerefentry>
                    <refentrytitle>v4lctl</refentrytitle>
                    <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
                </citerefentry>, <citerefentry>
                    <refentrytitle>xawtv</refentrytitle>
                    <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
                </citerefentry></para>
        </refsect1>
    </refentry>
</article>
